Guide to the Stanford Historical Society Oral History Program Interviews SC0932
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Faculty and Staff Interviews, 2007-2016; Series 5
  - Chu, Jean H., 2016
    Much of the oral history involves the many challenges she faced as Dean of Admissions. She describes the conflict she confronted between those who supported recruiting “well-rounded” students and others who favored “angular” students (“nerds” with extraordinary talents). Chu tells how she enabled the Department of Mathematics and later the departments of Music, Art, Drama, and Dance to review outstanding applicants in their fields, using the model created for athletes. She explains other policies she initiated and provides a detailed description of the review process, recounting some unusual cases as well as special efforts to recruit minorities and women.
    Chu outlines her service on the search committee that selected Gerhard Casper to be the new university president and the circumstances that led her to accept the role as his assistant. She contrasts her experiences as assistant to Lyman and Casper.
    Concluding her remarks, Chu recalls her experiences with her second husband, Steven Chu, when he received the Nobel Prize in physics.
  - Clark, Eve V., 2016-05
    Eve V. Clark, Richard W. Lyman Professor of Humanities and an internationally known linguist, reviews her life journey from the United Kingdom to the United States.
    Clark begins by discussing her childhood in Britain, emphasizing her relationship with her sister, and her early education. Clark recounts traveling with her family, reflecting particularly on her time in France and the impact that learning the French language at a young age has had on her. She then describes her time at the University of Edinburgh and her time studying abroad in Aux-en-Provence and Barcelona. Clark then discusses how her interest in linguistics developed, accrediting the year-long phonetics course she had previously completed and her decision to attend the Linguistics Institute at the University of California Los Angeles.
    Clark describes meeting her husband, Herb, completing her PhD, and coming to Stanford. Clark comments on her experience as an academic couple and on how she managed having a career and a family. Clark talks extensively about her research in language acquisition, describing past studies she has conducted and textbooks she has produced. She then details her work with undergraduates, the classes she has taught, and her time serving on multiple advisory boards. Clark then describes in more detail her time at Stanford, recounting how the Linguistics Department has evolved, the Loma Prieta earthquake, student discontent in the 1970s, the committees she had served on, and how being a woman has impacted her career, and her consciousness of the feminist movement.
    The interview concludes with Clark commenting on how Stanford can continue to cultivate a more hospitable environment for women and by reminiscing on how the students at Stanford, and their motivation and energy, has driven her decision to continue teaching at the university.
  - Cohen, Albert, 2010 Jun 18
    The interview was conducted by Jane Klickman, a retired Stanford administrator.
    Albert Cohen is the Wm. H. Bonsall Professor of Music, Emeritus at Stanford University.
    In his interview on June 18, 2010, Albert Cohen spoke about his time as a faculty member at Stanford and as Chairman of the Music Department from 1973 to 1987 as well as Acting Chair subsequently. He worked diligently and often struggled with the Stanford administration to improve the department’s facilities, particularly the Braun Center and Lully Archives, the faculty itself, and student experiences in the Music Department. He also talked about his research on 17th-18th century French music, musicology, and theory. He spoke about his pedagogical perspectives and other motivating factors in his career, as well as projects he is now working on in retirement.
  - Corn, Wanda M., 2011 May 1
    Wanda M. Corn’s interview traces her education in art history and eventual conversion to the emerging field of American art history in the 1960s. Corn discusses her experience of working with Lorenz Eitner and Al Elsen, the evolution and growth of the Department of Art and Art History, the relationship between the department and the Stanford museum, the trends in art history education, the gratification and challenges in chairing the department, the challenges facing the Stanford museum after the 1989 Loma Prieta Earthquake, her involvement in promoting the interests of woman faculty, her tenure as the third director of the Stanford Humanities Center, the John Cage celebration and the experience of hosting Spalding Gray, and the trips she led for Stanford Travel/Study. She concludes the interview with her thoughts on the Stanford Initiative for Creativity in the Arts.
    Having earned a BA (l963), MA (l965) and Ph.D. (l974) from New York University, Professor Wanda Corn taught at Washington Square College, the University of California, Berkeley, and Mills College before moving to Stanford University in Palo Alto, California in 1980. At Stanford she held the university's first permanent appointment in the history of American art and served as chair of the Department of Art and Art History and Acting Director of the Stanford Museum. From l992 to 1995 she was the Anthony P. Meier Family Professor and Director of the Stanford Humanities Center. In 2000, she became the Robert and Ruth Halperin Professor in Art History. She retired from teaching at Stanford in 2008. In 2009, she was the John Rewald Distinguished Visiting Lecturer, at the CUNY Graduate Center.
    A scholar of late nineteenth- and early twentieth-century American art and photography, Professor Corn has received fellowships from the American Council of Learned Societies, the Smithsonian American Art Museum, the Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, the Smithsonian Regents, the Stanford Humanities Center, the Radcliffe Institute of Advanced Study, and the Clark Institute of Art. In 2006-07, she was the Samuel H. Kress Professor at the Center for Advanced Study in the Visual Arts at the National Gallery of Art.
    She has won numerous teaching awards: in 2007 The Distinguished Teaching of Art History Award from the College Art Association; in 2002 the Phi Beta Kappa Undergraduate Teaching Award; and in 1974 the Graves Award for outstanding teaching in the humanities. In 2006, the Archives of American Art awarded her The Lawrence A. Fleischman Award for Scholarly Excellence in the Field of American Art History and in 2007 she received the Women's Caucus for Art Life Time Achievement Award in the Visual Arts. In 2003 she was the Clark Distinguished Visiting Professor at Williams College. She has served two terms on the Board of Directors of the College Art Association and two on the Commission for the Smithsonian American Art Museum. She served on the Advisory Board of the Georgia O’Keeffe Catalogue Raisonné, two terms on the Board of the Terra Foundation in American Art, and is today a trustee of the Wyeth Foundation in American Art.
    Active as a visiting curator, she had produced various books and exhibitions, including The Color of Mood: American Tonalism 1990-1910 (1972); The Art of Andrew Wyeth (l973); and Grant Wood: The Regionalist Vision (1983) and in 2011-12, Seeing Gertrude Stein, Five Stories. Her historiographic article for Art Bulletin, "Coming of Age: Historical Scholarship in American Art" (June l988), became a significant point of reference in the field as has her work on cultural nationalism in early American modernism. Her study of avant-garde modernist culture along the Atlantic rim, The Great American Thing: Modern Art and American Identity, 1915-35, was published by the University of California Press 1999. UC Press has recently published Professor Corn’s Women Building History about Mary Cassatt and the decorative program of murals and sculptures for the Woman’s Building at the 1893 Chicago World’s Columbian Exposition. She continues to research, write, and lecture on high, middle, and low culture interpretations of Grant Wood’s American Gothic.
  - Cottle, Richard W., 2015
    In the first of two interviews with Kandis Scott, Richard W. “Dick” Cottle gives a brief account of his birth in Chicago and education in neighboring Oak Park, Illinois. He reflects on his undergraduate and graduate studies in mathematics: first at Harvard and then (after a two-year interlude of prep-school mathematics teaching) at the University of California, Berkeley where he had the good fortune of working at the Radiation Laboratory and the Operations Research Center with George Dantzig. Cottle relates how upon completion of his doctoral studies, he took a position at Bell Telephone Laboratories for two years, accepted a one-year visiting faculty position with Stanford’s Operations Research Program (OR), and became a member of the tenure-line faculty when the OR Program became the Department of Operations Research. He talks about his rise through the academic ranks, his collaboration with George Dantzig (who had left Berkeley and joined Stanford), the formation of the Mathematical and Computational Sciences Program, the anti-Viet Nam War turbulence, his receipt of the U.S. Senior Scientist Award from the Alexander von Humboldt Foundation, and eventual chairmanship of the OR Department. He discusses the merger of the OR Department with the Engineering-Economic Systems Department and a second merger four years later with the Department of Industrial Engineering and Engineering Management.
    The second interview returns to the formation of the OR Department, its nature, its chairs, and the contemporaneous deans of the School of Engineering. Cottle recounts stories about his own chairmanship (which ended when the first of the two mergers occurred) and some of the challenges faced by the department. He also talks about events on campus, some of his closest friends on the Stanford faculty, and the effect that international recognition for his scholarly work had on his life at Stanford. He relates how he became involved with the writing of the book Stanford Street Names and other book projects. Responding to interviewer Kandis Scott’s questions, Cottle reflects on changes in the university, his sense of the most notable accomplishments of his career, and the challenges he faces going forward. The interview closes with comments on the influence of his family life.
  - DeBra, Daniel B., 2012 Apr 17
    Daniel B. DeBra begins with his education and his path towards research in mechanical engineering and eventually aeronautics and astronautics at Stanford. He then discusses his work at Stanford and the faculty and students with whom he worked closely, including Robert Cannon, Gene Franklin and Richard Van Patten.
    Daniel B. DeBra joined the Stanford faculty in 1964 and became emeritus professor in 1995. Before teaching at Stanford, Professor DeBra had worked at Lockheed Missile and Space Company, U.S. Air Force, and the Thermix Corporation.
    The awards Professor DeBra has received include the Industrial Research Award 100 for successful flight of drag-free satellite, 1973; the Distinguished Service Civilian Award, USAF SAB, 1982; the Thurlow Award, Institute of Navigation, 1983; and Distinguished Lecturer, ASPE, 1994.
    Professor DeBra received his B.E. in mechanical engineering from Yale in 1952, M.S. in mechanical engineering from M.I.T. in 1953, and a PhD. in engineering mechanics form Stanford in 1962.
  - Degler, Carl N., 2012-03-10
    Carl Degler begins with his decision to become a historian and his experience serving in the Army Air Force in World War II. He discusses his interests in labor unions, women’s history and black history. He continues with his position at Vassar followed by how he came to Stanford. The author of numerous books, Degler comments on his approach to writing and how he came to write about particular subjects and people in history. He concludes with his involvement in NOW (National Organization for Women) and his mentorship of women in academia.
  - Donaldson, Sarah S., 2015-01
    Dr. Sarah Donaldson begins her interviews by talking about her early life growing up in Portland, Oregon in the years during and after WWII. She describes her work during high school as a candy striper and nurse’s aide, and her later decision to study nursing at the University of Oregon. Dr. Donaldson speaks of her first job working for a cancer surgeon named Bill Fletcher who mentored her and ultimately encouraged her to go to medical school at a time when very few women were becoming doctors. She subsequently attended Dartmouth Medical School for two years and then transferred to Harvard for her last two years.
    Initially, Dr. Donaldson wanted to be a cancer surgeon but changed her mind and pursued radiation oncology. She took a residency at Stanford and specialized in pediatric radiation oncology when it was not yet a known field. Dr. Donaldson then became an assistant professor and set up a pediatric radiation oncology program at Stanford. She describes liking the small, family-like department she was in and feeling inspired by her colleagues to do her best work. While she enjoys all facets of her job, Dr. Donaldson mentioned particularly liking mentoring young female doctors and taking care of patients.
    Dr. Donaldson goes on to describe how many opportunities came to her because there were so few women in her field and how she was lacking a female mentor in her early years. She concludes the interview by talking about some of her more meaningful awards and honors as well as her publications that have had the most impact.
  - Doty, Andrew M., 2007 Jun 15
    Oral history interview conducted in June 2007 pertaining to his 30-year career in community relations and public affairs at Stanford. Topics include San Hill Road, Peter Coutts housing development, SLAC power line, commercial development of Stanford lands, and relations with Palo Alto and Santa Clara County.
    Andy Doty was born and raised in upstate New York. He joined the Army Air Corps and served in WWII. He came to Stanford in 1963 after working as a newspaper reporter in New York State, assistant director of public relations at Johns Hopkins University, and science and engineering editor at the University of Michigan. He retired as director of community relations in 1993. His tenure coincided with major land development issues at Stanford, including the Sand Hill Road project and the SLAC project. Doty’s interview sheds light on the interplay between “the (Stanford) trustees’ rights to develop their lands to the full extent if they wished and the neighbors’ political power to prevent as much expansion as they could.”
    Oral histories.; Community and college -- United States.; Schofield, Susan.; Doty, Andrew M.
  - Dreisbach, Robert H., 2016-03-28
    In this oral history, Robert H. Dreisbach, Stanford alumnus (AB Chemistry 1937) and Professor of Pharmacology, Emeritus, discusses growing up in Baker, Oregon. He touches on his father’s work on the farm, at a creamery, and as a grocer and his mother’s beekeeping, and he describes Boy Scout meetings and hiking trips with his troop. He discusses his undergraduate days at Stanford from 1933 to 1937, recalling attending dances, the El Capitan Eating Club, and serving as the manager of the Stanford baseball team. He recalls his chemistry and physics professors and describes how a talk at Stanford given by a researcher from the Department of Agriculture awakened his interest in pharmacology and helped to convince him to pursue the subject while in medical school at the University of Chicago.
    Dreisbach briefly recounts his experiences during World War II, which included working as an instructor at the Stanford Medical School and military service as a ward officer at Lovell General Hospital in Fort Devens, Massachusetts and at a hospital in the Panama Canal Zone. He describes the Stanford Medical School when it was located in San Francisco and provides his recollections of the rationale behind its move to campus, including Windsor Cutting’s involvement. He recounts the origins and evolution of his work, The Handbook of Poisoning and the way that poison control centers embraced the book.
    Dreisbach describes the expansion of the Pharmacology Department after Avram Goldstein arrived from Harvard University to assume its chairmanship and its move to the Stanford campus. He remembers Goldstein as a “go-getter” and relates how he secured space in the basement of the Stanford Museum for a laboratory. Dreisbach explains how concern about smog and air pollution led him to pursue research and writing on environmental issues. An avid hiker, he closes the interview, which was conducted on the eve of his 100th birthday, by offering advice for longevity--keep climbing summits.
  - Eddelman, William S., 2012 Feb 2
    William S. Eddelman arrived at Stanford in 1958 with undergraduate degrees in zoology and pre-med from the University of Reno. After obtaining his master’s degree in 1960 in Theater, Eddelman spent a year a Cornell University in a doctorate program before transferring back to Stanford. In 1965 he was awarded a Fulbright Scholarship to study theater and costume design in Venice, Italy at the Cini Institute. Upon his return to the States he taught for several years at the University of Calgary and returned to Stanford in 1970 as an associate professor in the Drama Department, and was later promoted to Assistant Professor. Eddelman took emeritus status in 2002, and taught until 2005.
    In this interview Eddelman describes his professional influences, including the global perspectives of Professors Wendell Cole and Doug Russell, and working for Dick Hay as a designer, and his own world-wide travels and interests. Eddelman references his life as a gay man in San Francisco and Stanford in the 1970s and 1980s. Eddelman also talks about his interaction with other Drama Department personnel, including Charles Lyons, and the substantial changes in the curriculum and degree focus in the Drama Department during the 1970s. Various projects Eddelman worked on at Stanford, including productions of Orasteia, Gaieties, and Twelfth Night, are described. Eddelman talks about his numerous and diverse interests in theater and costume design, including involvement with the Museum of Performance and Design in San Francisco, leading alumni tours of Venice and the Veneto for the Stanford Alumni Association, lecturing on Paris and Wagner, and cataloging his extensive postcard collection depicting various costume and design influences.
    Associate Professor Emeritus. William S. Eddelman has been a set and costume designer and a theater historian for more than forty years. At Stanford he has taught a wide variety of classes which have ranged from design, theater aesthetics, and musical theater to dramatic literature and cultural studies. Recently, he has taught a graduate seminar in international theater aesthetics and an undergraduate seminar called “Mapping and Wrapping the Body: The Psychology of Clothes.” He has taught several classes for Stanford Continuing Studies and in the last two quarters he has given classes on "Venice and the Veneto" and "Paris in the Jazz Age." He has co-led a tour for Stanford Alumni Travel in the Veneto part of Italy with a focus on Palladian Villas, and led a tour to Venice for carnival.
    As a very active board member of the San Francisco Performing Arts Library and Museum (which will be known in the future as the Museum of Performance and Design), Eddelman is involved in advising and purchasing materials for the new museum. He continues to work on a massive postcard collection that focuses on the history of costume, and is structuring a documentation project on the history of the costume and set design work at the Prague Quadrennials. Recently he completed a volume of photographs from nearly forty years ago.
  - Edwards, Mark W., 2016
    Mark W. Edwards, an emeritus professor in the Department of Classics, spent over two decades serving the Stanford community. Edwards influenced numerous undergraduate and graduate students at Stanford and at other institutions in the United States and Canada. The focus of this two-part interview is the breadth of Edwards’s teaching career and the evolution of his research interests, particularly his work related to Homer.
    Edwards’s academic success in classical languages began at his English grammar school during his teenage years. He explains how he chose Latin as his major at Bristol University and how, a few years later, he returned to Bristol to earn a second honors degree in Greek. Edwards pursued a master’s degree soon after, where he worked with Thomas Webster of University College London and began studying Homeric formulae. Both Webster and Homer proved to be strong influences on Edwards’s future career.
    After a year in London, Edwards moved to the United States as a Fulbright fellow at Princeton University and then accepted his first teaching position at Brown University. Edwards describes his impressions of mid-century America, the works of literature he covered in his classes, and his experience as a resident chaperone on campus. Edwards also discusses how not getting tenure at Brown prompted him to apply for a teaching position at Queen’s University in Ontario, Canada, where he taught for another seven years. He draws interesting comparisons between the two countries based on his student interactions, and provides more detailed information and examples about his work on Homeric formulae that developed over those fourteen years.
    In the second interview, Edwards describes his years at Stanford as a professor, department chair, and researcher. Edwards found many of his former mentors teaching at Stanford when he arrived in 1969. He taught a variety of Classics graduate courses and non-major undergraduate classes. Edwards also served as department chair for seven years. He discusses the highs and lows of the experience and details the two programs he was most proud of implementing: the Stanford in Greece program, which subsidized student travel in Greece, and the Webster Fund, named in honor of his mentor Thomas Webster, which supported the exchange of guest lecturers between Stanford and University College London.
    Over the course of thirty plus years teaching Homer’s work, Edwards widened his research to include studying the poet’s type scenes and story patterns. He personally appreciated those moments when Homer broke from the pattern and revealed more of himself. To share this expertise, Edwards wrote a well-received reader for the general public called Homer: Poet of the Iliad. After retiring early from Stanford, Edwards accepted an appointment at the University of California, Santa Cruz to teach Homer to undergraduates in Greek.
    Edwards concludes his interview with thoughts about how classics remains relevant in modern society. He points to his retirement reading group that recently studied the Odyssey. Through vicarious experience, Edwards feels the retirees gained knowledge from studying the text and relating it to the experiences they had during and after World War II. Edwards remarks that he takes great pleasure in these new interactions with classical texts he has studied his entire career.
  - Efron, Bradley, 2014-01-15